<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three positions concerning the 1 Authoritie of the Lords day. 2 State of the Church of Rome. 3 Execution of priests. All written vpon speciall occasions by Iames Balmford minister</title>
            <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855564</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855564</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1338:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three positions concerning the 1 Authoritie of the Lords day. 2 State of the Church of Rome. 3 Execution of priests. All written vpon speciall occasions by Iames Balmford minister</title>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556. Position maintained by I.B. before the late Earle of Huntingdon: viz. Priests are executed not for religion, but for treason. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston for Richard Boyle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes reprint of "A position maintained by I.B. before the late Earle of Huntingdon: viz. Priests are executed not for religion, but for treason" (STC 1334.5)--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Reissued with added general title page as "Carpenters chippes: or simple tokens of unfeined good will" (STC 1334)--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Durham University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Treason --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21060:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE POSITIONS <hi>Concerning the</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Authoritie of the Lords day.</item>
                  <item>2 State of the Church of Rome.</item>
                  <item>3 Execution of Prieſts.</item>
               </list> ALL WRITTEN VPON SPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall occaſions by IAMES BALM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORD <hi>Minister.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. Tim. 2. 7.</bibl> Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord giue thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in all things.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for RICHARD BOYLE. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21060:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21060:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND VERTVOVS LADY THE LADY MARGARET Countiſſe of Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland; IAMES BALMFORD</hi> (an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruant of Ieſus Christ) wiſheth all true honor in this life, and eternall glorie in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will honor them, who<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 30</note> honor me, <hi>ſaith the Lord of Lords: but in no one thing is that Lord more honored, than in a religious ſanctifying of the Lords day, which is an holy</hi> Signe<note place="margin">Exod. 31. 13</note> betweene the Lord and vs, <hi>that he doth ſanctifie vs to be his people, and that we ſanctifie him to be our God. Of which day it is thus written;</hi> If thou turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way<note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 13. 14.</note> thy foote from the Sabbath, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21060:3"/> doing thy will on mine holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate it as glorious to the Lord, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine owne waies, nor ſeeking thine own wil, nor ſpeaking a vaine word, Then ſhalt thou delight in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to mount vpon the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of <hi>Iacob</hi> thy father: For the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. <hi>In which words we may obſerue, 1. How highly the Lord estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his Sabbath. 2. How religiouſly the people of God are to ſanctifie the ſame. 3. That they, who make no conſcience of ſuch ſanctifying the Sabbath, can neuer delight in the Lord, what profeſsion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they make: and 4. That religious ſanctifying the Sabbath, as it is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part of</hi> Godlineſſe, <hi>ſo it hath a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promiſe of ſpeciall bleſsings, euen in this life. With theſe, and many other moſt gracious words, would God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21060:3"/> man to bee holy. But man hath ſought out many inuentions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, this conceipt;</hi> That the Lords day is not the ordinance of God. <hi>Vpon which ground many make no more conſcience of ſanctifying the Lords day, than of keeping holie daies (ſo called) ordained only by humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie; and ſome, by writing, not yet publiſhed, haue opened a gappe to much licentiouſneſſe. To ſloppe which gappe (as I may) I haue endeuoured to proue; That the Lords day is an ordinance of God. Which Poſition, with two other, concerning the Church of Rome, and Execution</hi> of Prieſts (<hi>written vpon iuſt occaſions, and by perſwaſion, the former of your Honor, the other of that right Chriſtian Noble-man, of moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble memorie,</hi> Henry <hi>late Earle of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington) I houe publiſhed vnder your Right Honorable name; As knowing your well informed zeale for the Lords day, and against the Synagogue of Rome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21060:4"/> to be ſuch, that</hi> England <hi>were the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt nation in the world, if all noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages were indued with the like; And (withall) hoping, that by theſe, and other more Diuine Treatiſes, the ſame ſhall be yet more and more inflamed, to the glorie of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your owne Soule.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="position">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21060:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST POSITION. THE LORDS DAY, <hi>commonly called Sonday,</hi> is an ordinance of <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F this bee true, that man is not to pollute <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 10 15</note> what God hath ſanctified; and If <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> (ſo called) were ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by God, I appeale to the conſciences of Gods people for iudgement, whether Man can make <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> common, without warrant from God himſelfe. If not; then <hi>Saturday</hi> is made common, either in regard of ſome Ceremonie, or by God himſelfe, for ſome other ſpeciall cauſe: As hee permitted a man vncleane, <note n="b" place="margin">Numb. 9, 10, 11.</note> or in a long iourney, to make common the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> (which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe was to be kept) in the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21060:5"/> That there was no Ceremony in the <hi>Iewes</hi> Sabbath to bee abrogated by the comming of Chriſt, I haue proued in another Diſcourſe, which with ſundrie points concerning the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> I am deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to publiſh hereafter, if God will. In the meane while, I deſire the Reader to conſider theſe briefe notes. 1. That the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was made <note n="c" place="margin">Mark. 2, 27. Deut. 5. 14, 15.</note> for man, yea ſo, that great care is had of ſeruants their reſt: which is no ceremoniall reſpect. 2. That the Learned do ſo diſagree about the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Ceremony, that one affirmeth <hi>Reſt,</hi> and denieth <hi>The ſeuenth day;</hi> another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the ſeuenth <hi>day,</hi> and denieth <hi>Rest</hi> to be the Ceremony. 3. That the fourth Commandement (which by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence gaue confirmation to <hi>Saturday</hi> before Chriſt his death, as now to <hi>Sonday</hi>) and euery word thereof, was <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 34. 1. &amp;</note> twiſe written by the finger of God in tables of ſtone: To ſhew, <note n="e" place="margin">19, 11. &amp; 20, 1. Deut. 4, 12, 13. 14. Gen. 17, 9, 10, 22, 23.</note> That the Decalogue, as it was preached to the Church immediately by God himſelfe, (before it was written by God, and deliuered to <hi>Moſes</hi> on the <hi>Mount</hi>) ſo it is eternall as God himſelfe; As the Goſpell preached by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21060:5"/> who was God as well as Man, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 19. Heb. 12. 27. 28. &amp; 21. &amp;c. &amp; 8. 2.</note> Whereas Circumciſion, and the ceremoniall Law, brought from God to the Church by <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> was temporall. 4. That none of the other nine Commandements (except the ſecond by Papiſts) is ſaid to be in any part ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall. 5. That <hi>Saturday</hi> of it ſelfe without the conſideration of <hi>Rest,</hi> or the number <hi>Seuen,</hi> (both which are alſo liable to <hi>Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>) cannot ſignifie any thing to come. 6. That it was ſanctified <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 2. 3.</note> in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> (though not expreſſely named) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not inſtituted at the firſt, to ſignifie Chriſt to come, and therefore no more a Ceremonie, to be abrogated by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, than Marriage which <note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 2. 23. 24.</note> was alſo inſtituted in Paradiſe, and is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely applied to ſignifie <note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 25. &amp;c.</note> the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall coniunction betweene Chriſt and his Church.</p>
            <p>But let it be ſuppoſed, that <hi>Saturday</hi> was ceremoniall. What other thing is thereupon to be inferred, but, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ceaſeth to be <hi>Gods Holy day?</hi> But can we imagine, that God would take no order, that another day ſhould be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21060:6"/> for his owne worſhip? Did hee ſanctifie a Sabbath in the time of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and when there were none to keep it but <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue?</hi> And would he not appoint a Sabbath in the time <note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 19, 28.</note> of <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> &amp; when his people were <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 2, 2, 3.</note> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, his <hi>Sonne</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 110. 1, 2, 3.</note> King in <hi>Sion,</hi> and the power of his rod ſuch, that (as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied) <hi>His people ſhould come willingly at the time of aſſembling his army in holy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</hi> Did he himſelfe, not only inſtitute a <hi>Seuenth day</hi> in Paradiſe to our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed it alſo <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 20, 1, 8.</note> to the <hi>Iewes?</hi> And will he leaue <hi>Christians</hi> (<note n="n" place="margin">1. Pet. 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Achoſen generation, and Royall Priest-hood</hi>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Sabbath ſanctified by his Diuine authoritie; conſidering the Sabbath <note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 31, 13, 17.</note> is a ſigne that wee may know that hee is the Lord, who doth ſanctifie vs to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? And to what other end, than <note n="p" place="margin">Ezech. 46, 1, 2, 3.</note> to worſhip him our Sanctifier? Laſtly, when the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> was not kept in the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, becauſe of vncleanneſſe, or a long iourney, did God ſuffer it either to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or tranſlated, as it ſeemed good to the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> Nay, he himſelfe <note n="q" place="margin">Num. 19, 10, 11.</note> nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated the fourteenth day of the ſecond
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21060:6"/> moneth to be kept for the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> in thoſe caſes. Was God ſo zealous for the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> a ceremoniall Sabbath, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore temporall? And would hee neglect <hi>The ſeuenth day,</hi> a morall Sabbath, and therefore eternall? Sith in the fourth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he commandeth <hi>A ſeuenth day</hi> to be holy for euer. For as hee commaundeth <hi>Worſhip</hi> vpon the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> preſcribing neither <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> nor <hi>Christian;</hi> ſo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth <hi>A ſeuenth day</hi> to be the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> preſcribing neither <hi>Saturday,</hi> nor <hi>Sonday.</hi> So that the fourth Commandement and euery word thereof (without any alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) doth belong to Chriſtians, as well as to Iewes. If ſo, then I conclude, that (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saturday</hi> were made common, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of a ceremony, or for ſome other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect) ſome other day in place thereof was ſanctified to holy worſhip, by diuine authoritie.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected, that whereas by God himſelfe, the inſtitution of the <hi>Iewes</hi> their Sabbath, was commanded vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation therof promulgated to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> with the reſt of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue: It is ſtrange, that it ſhould ceaſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21060:7"/> (not of it ſelfe, as being ceremoniall, but) for ſome other ſpeciall cauſe; and another day appointed in the place thereof, and that by God, and yet it is not knowne, whether immediately, or by whom, God made this alteration; I anſwere; that as God, at the laſt day, will iudge the world <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 17. 31</note> by the man whom he hath appointed; ſo in the meane time he doth gouerne the Church by his <hi>Sonne,</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 2. 6. Joh. 5. 22. Col. 3. 1. &amp; 2. 20.</note> whom hee hath placed King in <hi>Sion.</hi> So that whatſoeuer the <hi>Sonne</hi> doth is authenticall, and of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine authoritie. Not only becauſe hee is God <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 9. 5. 1. Tim. 6. 14. 15. 16.</note> bleſſed for euer, but alſo in that he is that great Prophet <note n="u" place="margin">Deut. 18. 18. 19. Act. 3. 20. 22.</note> like vnto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> whom we are to heare; For he doth nothing of himſelfe <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 3. 32. 33. &amp; 8. 28.</note> but as his <hi>Father</hi> taught him. But that Chriſt the <hi>Sonne</hi> of the liuing God ſanctified that other Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, I thus proue.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Sonne</hi> bee as faithfull in all his owne houſe, in things concerning the worſhip of God, <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 3. 2. 5. 6.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; If Chriſt bee the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 4. 19. 20. 25. 26.</note> who ſhould teach vs all things: If <hi>Moſes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed euery thing belonging to the Tabernacle <note n="z" place="margin">Exod. 25. 9. 38.</note> euen to a paire of ſnuffers;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21060:7"/> If the things belonging to the houſe of God, befew in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of thoſe which belonged to the Tabernacle of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe the houre is come, when <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 4. 23.</note> wee muſt worſhip the <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> that is, ſpiritually, <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3. 3.</note> without the intolerable <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 15. 10 Gal. 4. 3.</note> yoke of <hi>carnall</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 9. 1. 10.</note> rites; If a <hi>Sabbath</hi> be as neceſſarie vnto the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt his houſe, as a paire of ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the ſeruice of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: then (without doubt) <hi>Saturday</hi> being made common, Chriſt appointed ſome other day to be a Sabbath vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as the Leuiticall Prieſt-hood being ceaſed, <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 7. 11. 12. Epheſ. 4. 8. 11. 12.</note> he ſanctified another Miniſtery vnder the <hi>Gospell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, whereas Chriſt came <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 5. 17.</note> not to breake, but to fulfill the Law, and the Law doth command one day of ſeuen to be a Sabbath, as is ſaid; Therefore Chriſt did either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme <hi>Saturday,</hi> or ſanctifie ſome other day of the weeke: but that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed <hi>Saturday</hi> none will affirme, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he ſanctified ſome other day of the weeke: Which to be <hi>Sonday,</hi> I thus proue.</p>
            <p>We ſee that <hi>Sonday</hi> is generally kept holy in all the Churches of Chriſt; And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21060:8"/> there is nothing to the contrarie, but that it hath been ſanctified In, and ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time. If then God, by Chriſt, hath ſanctified a Sabbath vnto <hi>Christians,</hi> it muſt neceſſarily follow, that either the Church hath neuer regarded, but negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ordinance of GOD, for many hundred yeeres; or elſe, that <hi>Sonday</hi> was ſanctified by <hi>Christ.</hi> But the former is not eaſily to bee admitted, conſidering the Church <note n="g" place="margin">1. Tim. 3, 15.</note> is the <hi>Pillar of truth,</hi> therefore the later more willingly to be receaued.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the <hi>Sonne</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 5, 19, 21.</note> doth whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Father</hi> doth; and if the <hi>Father</hi> hath committed all iudgement to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Exo. 22, 23</note> that all men ſhould honor the <hi>Sonne,</hi> as they honor the <hi>Father;</hi> then, as the <hi>Father</hi> ſanctified <hi>A ſeuenth day;</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 2, 2, 3</note> as on which he finiſhed his works of Creation, and <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 1, 19. 20.</note> was declared mightily to be the liuing God, <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 31, 13, 17.</note> to his owne honor, (and therfore <note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 58, 13.</note> did call it <hi>mine holy day</hi>) For it was not a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sanctification</hi> (as ſome dreaming of a ceremony, do imagine) but <hi>A Signe</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> people of their <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> that is, A toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or memorial that they may know that the <hi>Creator</hi> is the <hi>Lord,</hi> who doth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21060:8"/> ſanctifie them to bee his people: So the <hi>Sonne</hi> ſanctified that day, <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 15, 16, 17, 57. Rom. 8, 34. &amp;</note> whereon he conſummated, and ſealed his workes of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and was declared mightilie, <note n="p" place="margin">1, 4.</note> to be the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to his owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Which was <hi>Sonday,</hi> called for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, <note n="q" place="margin">Reuel. 1, 10.</note> 
               <hi>The Lords day,</hi> as ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared hereafter. For <note n="*" place="margin">Leuit. 23, 15, 16. Matth. 28, 1, 5, 6.</note> vpon that day <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 4, 25</note> Chriſt roſe againe for our <hi>Iustification,</hi> and manifeſted himſelfe to be <note n="ſ" place="margin">Act. 1, 6, 7, 8, &amp; 2. 1.</note> the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall King of his Church, by miraculous giuing the power of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> vnto his Apoſtles. So that, <hi>Sonday</hi> is a ſigne, or memoriall vnto <hi>Christians,</hi> that they may know, that the <hi>Redeemer</hi> is the <hi>Lord,</hi> who doth ſanctifie them.</p>
            <p>If it bee demaunded why Chriſtians ſhould ſo honor the <hi>Sonne,</hi> that they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the <hi>Father;</hi> and ſo celebrate the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> that they neglect the memoriall of the <hi>Creator?</hi> Seeing it is written, <note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 4, 23.</note> 
               <hi>The houre is come, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth;</hi> &amp; by the light of nature <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 14, 15, &amp; 17, 23, 24</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> is glorified, as hee is <hi>Creator;</hi> I anſwere: That it is not ſo; for <hi>A ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day,</hi> (though not <hi>Saturday</hi>) is ſtill ſanctified. Which to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21060:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> be ſufficient to celebrate the <hi>Creator,</hi> the fourth Commandement preſcribeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this, nor that ſeuenth day, but one of ſeuen, doth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proue. So that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Sonday</hi> is <hi>The Lords day,</hi> and withall <hi>A ſeuenth day,</hi> we may obſerue, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 13.</note> glorifie the <hi>Father</hi> in the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and celebrate the <hi>Creator</hi> with the <hi>Redeemer.</hi> By whom a New creation (though ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall) was performed <note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 65. 17. &amp; 66. 21. 22</note> according to the prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly; If it may appeare by the word, that <hi>Sonday</hi> was confirmed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles practiſe, and preceptiue execution, then <hi>Sonday</hi> hath authoritie, not from the Church, but from Chriſt. But it appeareth by the word, that <hi>Sonday</hi> was ſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; therfore it hath authority not from the Church, but from <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the ſequele of the Maior may better appeare, I will manifeſt the Minor, by theſe three places of holy writ: viz. <hi>Act.</hi> 20, 6, 7. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16, 2. and <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1, 10. For, in the firſt place three things are to be obſerued. 1. That <hi>Paul</hi> abode at <hi>Troas</hi> ſeuen daies. 2. That it is not ſaid; The Diſciples were called of purpoſe to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21060:9"/> his preaching, but <hi>Being come together to breake bread,</hi> that is, to be partakers of the Lords Supper. And 3. That, ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part on the morow, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, till midnight; Then it will appeare, that <hi>Sonday</hi> (there called <hi>The first day of the weeke,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Iewes</hi> their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to whom <hi>Saturday</hi> was the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, that is, the laſt day of the weeke) was ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to holy meetings, and exerciſes. And that <hi>Paul</hi> waited (as at <hi>Philippi</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Act. 16. 12. 13.</note> for the Sabbath of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſo) at <hi>Troas</hi> for the Chriſtians their Lords day. Which he would not haue done, being an Apoſtle, and hauing ſuch haſt of departure, if <hi>Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> had not been ſanctified, by greater authority than the ordinary authority of the Elders and Brethren.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected, that (according to the originall) the words bee <hi>One of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bathes,</hi> in the two former places, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is vncertaine, whether <hi>Sonday</hi> bee meant in thoſe places, rather than <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> I anſwere; That, by the ſame reaſon, it is vncertaine whether our bleſſed <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> did ariſe againe the third day <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 4.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures: For all the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelists</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21060:10"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 28. 1 Mark. 16. 2. Luke 24. 1. Ioh. 20. 1.</note> vſe the ſame words, when they report, That <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> went to ſeeke Chriſt, when he was riſen.</p>
            <p>But more fully to confute this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, three things are to be noted. 1. That in the originall the numerall (<hi>One</hi>) is put for the ordinall (<hi>First.</hi>) For <hi>Marke</hi> hauing ſaid in the ſecond verſe of his 16. chapter, <hi>One of the Sabbathes,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> her ſeeking of Chriſt, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the words in the 9. verſe, and ſaith; <hi>The First day;</hi> ſhewing that Chriſt was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. And that <hi>Sabbathes</hi> is put for <hi>Weekes.</hi> As in <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25. 8. it is written; <hi>Thou ſhalt number 7. Sabbathes</hi> (that is weekes) <hi>of yeeres.</hi> Secondly it is to be obſerued, That in both places only Chriſtians are ſaid to haue theſe meetings: For they, who came together, are called <hi>Diſciples</hi> &amp; <hi>Churches,</hi> and are ſaid <hi>To breake bread,</hi> that is, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the <hi>Communion</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 16. 17. 18.</note> which none but Chriſtians may do. And therefore in both places the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> in two ſundry wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth theſe words; <hi>The first day of the weeke,</hi> rather than, <hi>The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day,</hi> more diſtinctly to expreſſe that day, which was ſanctified by Chriſtians.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21060:10"/> Whereas at <hi>Philippi,</hi> where no Diſciples were as yet, <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 16. 12. 18.</note> to go on <hi>The Sabbath,</hi> to the place, where the <hi>Iewes</hi> were wont to pray, after he had bin there certaine daies. For what neede had the Chriſtians being none but themſelues, to neglect the <hi>Lords day,</hi> for the <hi>Iewes Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath?</hi> Thirdly, note that it is ſaid; <hi>Euery first day. 1. Cor.</hi> 16. 2. and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any probability, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would haue them come together euery <hi>Saturday.</hi> If not, it followeth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, that by <hi>The first day of the weeke Sonday</hi> is vnderſtood.</p>
            <p>In 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1. 2. we are yet further to conſider, that the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>As I haue ordained in the Churches of Galatia,</hi> which argueth <hi>Generality,</hi> and <hi>Euery first day,</hi> which argueth <hi>Perpetuity.</hi> So that by this place, holy aſſemblies vpon <hi>Sonday</hi> may ſeeme, as generall in thoſe times, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed for euer, by a preceptiue exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For as in this ſpeech <note n="d" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Let euery one, that calleth on the name of Christ, depart from iniquitie,</hi> a preceptiue exhortation to call on the name of Chriſt, is implied, howſoeuer only departing from iniquity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21060:11"/> bee expreſſely commaunded. So in this ſpeech deliuered by an Apoſtle, <hi>Euery first day of the weeke let euery one of you put aſide,</hi> is implied a preceptiue exhortation, to come together vpon the firſt day of the weeke, howſoeuer only putting aſide be expreſly commanded.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected, That theſe meetings were only to gather for the Saints, I deny it. For it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 7. That the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples came together to break bread, which importeth other holy exerciſes. Againe, If no more were vnderſtood than expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, then Chriſtians co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed in the faith, were leſſe religious vpon their ſetled and ſanctified holy day, than they were ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, if not euery day, at their firſt ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into their holy profeſſion. For then they mette together <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 2. 42. 46.</note> not only to breake bread, but vnto doctrine alſo, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Laſtly, The Apoſtle, who was ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to ſanctifie the Lords day at <hi>Troas,</hi> would (no doubt) reproue in this place ſo great neglect of <hi>The Lords day,</hi> if ſuch a matter were then to be ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 10. if nothing elſe were vrged, but the conſideration of the two
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21060:11"/> former places, it doth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly appeare, that by <hi>The Lords day</hi> is meant <hi>The first day of the weeke</hi> (now called <hi>Sonday</hi>) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement of all the learned. Againſt which ſtreame to ſtriue, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a doubt without reaſon (at leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) is to bewray a proud conceipt of a priuate opinion. But howſoeuer this be ſufficient, yet for the godly their ſake, I will ſay ſomewhat more than inough.</p>
            <p>It is the iudgement of the learned (and I ſee nothing to the contrarie) That as <hi>Paul</hi> praying in the Temple <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 22. 17</note> fell into a traunce; ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> ſanctifying the Lords day, was rauiſhed in ſpirit. If ſo, how can we imagine, That <hi>Iohn</hi> baniſhed <note n="f" place="margin">Reuel. 1. 9</note> in the iſle <hi>Patmos,</hi> hauing no cauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine him, nor occaſion to induce him, ſhould rather ſanctifie the <hi>Iewes</hi> Sabbath, than the Chriſtians holy day? Againe, If we find theſe titles, <hi>Our Lord,</hi> or <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> that he is called <note n="g" place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 14. 15.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord of Lords,</hi> and by the title <hi>Lord</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 4. 5. 6. Epheſ. 4. 4. 5. 6.</note> diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> ſo that in few (if any) places of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it is applied diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by way of title, to any but to the <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21060:12"/> will any who ſaith <hi>Ieſus is the Lord</hi> (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by the <hi>Spirit of God</hi>) make any doubt that by <hi>The Lords day</hi> is meant that day, which was eſpecially ſanctified to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Chriſt? And will any Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that which is ſaid, be yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, whether that were <hi>Sonday,</hi> or no? Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Beza</hi> in his note vpon 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 2. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, That, in one <hi>Greeke</hi> copy, theſe very words, <hi>The Lords,</hi> be added to <hi>Euery first day.</hi> Which ſheweth manifeſtly, That not the <hi>Iewes</hi> Sabbath, but <hi>The first day of the weeke</hi> was called <hi>The Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then in 3. places of holy Scriptures written by 3. holy men inſpired by the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> (of whom <hi>Luke</hi> was an <hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist, Paul</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> Apoſtles) we finde, <hi>The first day of the weeke</hi> (according to the computation of the <hi>Iewes</hi>) now called <hi>Sonday,</hi> ſanctified to the worſhip of God, yea ſo, That <hi>Paul</hi> waited for it at <hi>Troas,</hi> and doth preceptiuely exhort the ſame (though by implication) to be ſanctified euery weeke amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as in other places; and it obtained the name of <hi>The Lords day,</hi> as being ſpecially ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to the honor of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> wee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21060:12"/> may conclude, That it appeareth by the <hi>Word,</hi> That the <hi>Lords day</hi> called <hi>Sonday,</hi> was confirmed by the Apoſtles practiſe, and preceptiue exhortation.</p>
            <p>Now the Minor, or aſſumption of the former ſyllogiſme is manifeſted, I am to confirme the ſequele of the Maior, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Wherein two things are to bee proued. 1. That <hi>The Lords day</hi> was not eſtabliſhed by the ordinarie authoritie of the Church. And 2. That it was eſtabliſhed by the Diuine authoritie of our <hi>Sauiour Christ.</hi> The reaſon of both is; becauſe it was eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The former (though euident by that which is ſaid) will yet further appeare; If we grant, That the <hi>Primitiue</hi> Church at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed as much to the Apoſtles, who firſt <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 6. 10.</note> planted the ſame, and (for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that worke of God) were <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 2. 4.</note> indued with extraordinary gifts, inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> &amp; inſtructed <note n="l" place="margin">&amp; 1. 3.</note> by <hi>Christ</hi> 40. daies after his reſurrection, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did to <hi>Moſes</hi> their Law-giuer. But while <hi>Moſes</hi> liued the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> tooke all their directions from him; yea ſo, That not only in difficult caſes <note n="m" place="margin">Leuit. 24. 11. 12. Num. 15. 32. 33. &amp; 27. 1. 2.</note> of <hi>blaſphemy,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21060:13"/> Prophaning the Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Daughters inheritance,</hi> not formerly ruled by <hi>Moſes,</hi> they came to him to know the minde of the Lord; but alſo in all things about the Tabernacle <note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 31. 3. 6. &amp; 39. 37. 42. &amp; 25. 38. 40.</note> euen to a paire of ſnuffers, the worke-men, though miraculouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with cunning, were altogether di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by him, who had his inſtructions immediately from GOD. Can we then thinke That the Diſciples came together euery firſt day of the week of themſelues, though by generall conſent, without the authoritie of the Apoſtles ſo directing them? If they had attempted ſuch a thing, how could they haue anſwered this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 36. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Came the word of God out from you?</hi> A queſtion made by the Apoſtle in a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> miſliking <hi>Pauls</hi> directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s touching ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing tongues without interpretation, and women in the Churches, would happily ſay, That they were of another opinion. So that it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth this reply. <hi>But I pray you conſider, that the Apostles are the first teachers of the Church, hauing receiued their instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Christ his mouth, or by reuelation, therefore the Church is to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21060:13"/> be ordered by them.</hi> If then worke-men, cunning by inſpiration, could not make a paire of ſnuffers without <hi>Moſes</hi> his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor the Church in <hi>Corinth,</hi> by it owne authority, permit the manifeſtation of the extraordinary gift of the ſpirit to be in their publique aſſemblies without interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, could <hi>The Lords day</hi> (a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great regard) bee eſtabliſhed without the authoritie of the Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>Againe, Whereas the Apoſtle hauing reproued certaine male vſages amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and taken ſome order for reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſe of <hi>Loue feaſts,</hi> which were of good vſe at the firſt, but tending, at laſt, to the prophaning of the Lords <hi>Supper,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth thus, <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Other things wil I ſet in order, when I come:</hi> Is it not euident, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church could do litle, or nothing, much leſſe eſtabliſh <hi>Sonday</hi> to bee the Lords day, without Apoſtolique autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? Laſtly; If <hi>Titus</hi> an <hi>Euangelist</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Tit. 1. 5.</note> could not reforme <hi>Creta,</hi> nor ordaine <hi>Elders,</hi> but as he was appointed by <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſee not but that all things in the Church were orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ordained by the Apoſtles. If by the Apoſtles, then by Chriſt. Which is the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21060:14"/> ſecond point in the Maior now to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p>If we receiue the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as the Word of God, why not their conſtitutions accordingly? I meane not vnwritten verities, or rather the very lies of Antichriſtian Papiſts, but ſuch ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as are mentioned and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Word. For the Apoſtles were <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 1. 2. 8. &amp; 22. 15.</note> choſen, and faithfull witneſſes of thoſe things, which they haue heard and ſeene; and (no doubt) as faithfull <note n="s" place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 25 1. Tim. 3. 14. 15.</note> in all the houſe of God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was about the Tabernacle, and in gouerning <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi> did not direct the worke-men to make any thing, no not a paire of ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, but according to the patterne, which he ſaw in the mount, and in the ſaid caſes of <note n="t" place="margin">Leuit. 24. 12. 13. Num. 15. 34 35. &amp; 27. 5 6.</note> 
               <hi>Blasphemy, Prophaning the Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Daughters inheritance</hi> anſwered not of himſelf, but conſulted with God. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles did not preſcribe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but with ſuch authority, that <hi>Paul</hi> (and ſo all) might ſay, <note n="u" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 23.</note> 
               <hi>I haue receiued of the Lord</hi> (to wit <hi>Christ) that which I haue alſo deliuered vnto you.</hi> But what neede theſe inferences? Doth not the Apoſtle
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21060:14"/> charge <note n="*" place="margin">&amp; 14. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Euery man that thinketh himſelfe to be a Prophet, or ſpirituall, to acknowledge that the things hee writeth to them, are the Commandements of the Lord?</hi> If the things which he then writ, viz. Directions about <hi>Prophecy, Speaking with ſtrange tongues,</hi> and <hi>Silence of women in the Church,</hi> were the Commandements of the Lord, can we thinke him to be a true Prophet, and ſpirituall indeed, who perceiuing <hi>The Lords day</hi> to haue been eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles, will not acknowledge it to be a Commandement of the Lord?</p>
            <p>If it bee demaunded, when our Lord commanded his <hi>Holy day:</hi> I anſwere; The faithfulnes and credit of the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, are ſufficient to perſwade an humble Chriſtian to receiue it as the Lords ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; though it be not certainly knowne when Chriſt did ordaine it. But it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that he gaue commandement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame, within thoſe 40. daies after his reſurrection. <hi>When</hi> (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note n="x" place="margin">Act. 1. 2. 3</note> in expreſſe words) <hi>he gaue, through the Holy Ghost, Commandements vnto the Apostles, whom he had choſen, and ſpake of thoſe things which appertaine to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21060:15"/> of God.</hi> Now doth it not eſpecially appertaine to the kingdome of God, that Chriſtians ſhould ſanctifie their Lords day, wherein <note n="y" place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 23. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Christ</hi> crucified, <note n="z" place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>The mystery</hi> of godlines, and <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Sauiour</hi> of the world ſhould be <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 10. 42. 43.</note> preached, as well as the <hi>Iewes</hi> had their Sabbath, on which <hi>Moſes, A ſchoole master</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3. 24</note> 
               <hi>to Christ,</hi> and <hi>A minister of the Letter</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 6.</note> which killeth was <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 15. 21.</note> preached?</p>
            <p>Againe, If in thoſe 40. daies Chriſt <note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 4. 8. 10. 11.</note> appointed what Miniſters ſhould teach his Church for euer; how can it be, but that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo he appointed ſome Sabbath, wheron they ſhould ordinarily performe the worke of their miniſterie, as hee was wont <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 4. 16.</note> to do himſelfe? Seeing it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 110. 2. 3.</note> That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of his rod ſhould be ſuch, that <hi>His people ſhould come willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the time of aſſembling his army in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beauty.</hi> Seeing his <hi>Father</hi> (whoſe works <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 5. 19.</note> he imitateth) appointed <note n="h" place="margin">Leuit. 16. 2. 29.</note> as an high Prieſt, ſo a time, when (once in a yeere) he ſhould enter into the <hi>Most holy place;</hi> and as other Prieſts, <note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 29. 44. 38.</note> ſo morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifices; and conſidering it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note n="k" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>To euery purpoſe vnder heauen there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21060:15"/> is an appointed time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly; If the <hi>Sonne</hi> be like his <hi>Father,</hi> as in teaching his Apoſtles 40. daies (for ſo long <note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 24. 12. 18. &amp; 39. 42.</note> was <hi>Moſes</hi> with the <hi>Father</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mount) ſo in ſpeaking thoſe things which appertaine to the kingdome of God, as his <hi>Father</hi> taught <hi>Moſes</hi> al things belonging to the furniſhing of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; and If the <hi>Sonne</hi> be like his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in ſanctifying a day to his owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, as hath been declared, Why may not Chriſtians beleeue, that Chriſt ſanctified <hi>The Lords day</hi> within thoſe 40. daies, as the <hi>Father</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Deut. 9. 9</note> confirmed <hi>The ſeuenth day</hi> in thoſe 40. daies, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was with him on the mount? And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is te be obſerued, That the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 19. 26.</note> aſſembled the two firſt daies of the two weeks immediatly following <hi>Christ</hi> his reſurrection; and that our Lord, not only of purpoſe ſanctified both thoſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies with his holy and miraculous preſence, but alſo (immediatly before his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi>) commanded his Apoſtles <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 1. 4. 5. 7. 9.</note> to wait, a few daies, for the promiſe of the <hi>Father;</hi> Which (by his prouidence, in whoſe power bee times, and ſeaſons, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21060:16"/> Chriſt affirmed euen in this caſe) was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled <note n="p" place="margin">Mark. 16. 1. 2. Leuit. 23. 15. 16. Act. 2. 1. 4. 14.</note> vpon a <hi>Sonday;</hi> and at the ſame time the Apoſtles firſt began the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their miniſtery, and preached Chriſt publiquely: But publique preaching <note n="q" place="margin">Num. 10. 7. 8. Iſa. 58. 1. Ezech. 44. 23. 24. Act. 23. 14. 42.</note> is a ſpeciall worke of the Sabbath day. It may therefore bee gathered, That Chriſt appointed his Apoſtles to ſanctifie <hi>Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> whereon he would manifeſt himſelfe <note n="r" place="margin">&amp; 1. 6. 7. 8</note> to be King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as his <hi>Father</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted <hi>A ſeuenth day,</hi> as on which, he was manifeſted to bee GOD of heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>To conclude, If <hi>Saturday</hi> were made common, not by man, but by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and that not for a Ceremony, but for ſome other cauſe; If God ſanctified a Sabbath as well to Chriſtians, as to <hi>Iewes;</hi> If euery ordinance of Chriſt were an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; If Chriſt were as faithfull in all his owne houſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> about the Tabernacle; If Chriſt came to fulfill the fourth Commandement, which preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth one day of ſeuen; If the Church of God bee not eaſily to bee condemned as neglecting the ordinance of God in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying <hi>Sonday</hi> for many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeeres;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21060:16"/> If <hi>Christ</hi> were like his <hi>Father</hi> in ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that day to his owne honor, whereon he was declared to be the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God, and King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to wit <hi>Sonday;</hi> If the day be ſo appointed, that the <hi>Creator</hi> is glorified with the <hi>Redeemer;</hi> If it appeare by the <hi>Word,</hi> that the firſt day of the week was confirmed by the Apoſtles practiſe, and preceptiue exhortation; If by the firſt day of the week be meant that day wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt did riſe againe, and that was <hi>Sonday;</hi> If in the <hi>Word Sonday</hi> be called <hi>The Lords day</hi> to the honour of Chriſt our Lord; If the warrant of <hi>Sonday</hi> conſiſteth not in the ordinarie authoritie of the Church, becauſe it was eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles; If euery ſpirituall man be to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ordinances of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to bee the ordinances of the Lord; and If the Apoſtles were informed by Chriſt touching the <hi>Lords day</hi> within thoſe 40. daies after his reſurrection: I may ſafely hold this my Poſition; <hi>The Lords day, commonly called Sonday, is an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="position">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21060:17"/>
            <head>THE SECOND POSITION. THE CHVRCH OF ROME IS not the Catholike Church, neither yet <hi>hath continued an apparant mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſame, euer ſince the Apostles time.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church is ſaid to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, in regard of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſality thereof; for this word Catholike ſignifieth Vniuerfall. The Vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof conſiſteth in Times, Perſons and Places. For there is no age of the world, no nation on the earth, and no ſort of people, that can be exempted from the ſame. And therefore it is called The ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Hieruſalem, and ſaid to be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 22. 23.</note> of the firſt borne, which are written in heauen. So that we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, That as there hath been euer an head (to wit Chriſt) ſo there hath been
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21060:17"/> alſo a body (to wit the Church) ſome where, or other, but the Church of Rome is a particular Church, confined within a certaine compaſſe, and hath not been a Church but ſince Chriſt his comming in the fleſh, therfore it is not the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Catholique Church is an obiect of faith, according to the Apoſtles Creed, and therefore inuiſible, howſoeuer the members thereof (called by <hi>Peter, Liuely</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 5. Heb. 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſtones</hi>) be viſible, as they be men: <hi>For faith is the euidence of things not ſeene:</hi> But the Church of Rome is viſible, therefore not the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I grant, that as one man, ſo one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church may be called Catholike, but it is only in regard of the Catholique faith, (as being one, &amp; the ſame through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Catholique Church) which that one man, or that one Church profeſſeth: But the Church of Rome profeſſeth not (indeed) the Catholike faith (as ſhal be in part ſhewed hereafter) therefore (in no ſenſe) it can be truly called Catholique. But ſuppoſe it held the Catholique faith, yet were it not, for that cauſe, an obiect of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21060:18"/> faith according to the Apoſtles Creed, more than a particular man, or any other particular Church holding the faith. Here it is to be vnderſtood, that howſoeuer we may ſay: This man, or that Church is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, yet we may not ſay, and ſpeake properly, This is the Catholique man, or That is the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Rome holdeth not the Catholike faith, neither yet hath done for many yeeres, may be demonſtrated in ſundry fundamentall points. Let it be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to produce though but one, yet that moſt fundamental, ſith it is called by an excellency, <hi>The Word of faith,</hi> preached<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 6. 8.</note> by all the Apoſtles. And the rather that One, becauſe it is the principall argument of that worthy Epiſtle, which <hi>Paul</hi> wrote<note place="margin">Cap. 1. 8.</note> to the Romans, whoſe faith was then pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed throughout the whole world. So that, if the Church of Rome ſwarue from this truth, it is manifeſt that it is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, not of the true members of the Primitiue Church of Rome, but of the troublers of that Church, of whom <hi>Paul</hi> thus writeth: <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 16. 17. 18.</note> 
               <hi>marke them diligently which cauſe diuiſion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21060:18"/> and auoid them: For they that are ſuch ſerue not the Lord Ieſus, but their owne bellies, and with faire ſpeech and flattering deceiue the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> But what is that moſt fundamentall point? Euen that ſame, which <hi>Paul,</hi> after a large and learned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſetteth downe as his perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iudgement in theſe words; <hi>Therefore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 28.</note> 
               <hi>we conclude, that a man is iustified by faith, without the workes of the Law.</hi> But the Church of Rome, that now is, holdeth, and for many yeeres hath held, That a man is iuſtified both by faith, and works, contrary to the concluſion; therefore the Church of Rome is not Catholique, but Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p n="5">5 I ſay Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it may be proued ſuch, by many reaſons, and that becauſe it erreth in this point; but I only propound to wiſe and religious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration this deduction: That Antichriſtian Apoſtaſy, or Antichriſt, is called, <hi>The My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 7</note> 
               <hi>of iniquitie,</hi> that is, a myſticall iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is, an iniquity which is indeed ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but not perceiued, as Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Mystery of godlineſſe,</hi> that is, a<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 16.</note> myſtical godlineſſe, that is, godlineſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21060:19"/> but not perceiued. But wherefore is Antichriſt a myſticall iniquitie? Becauſe his Righteouſneſſe, though glorious in ſhew, is iniquity in deed, becauſe he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 4. Rom. 3 27. 1. Cor. 4. 1. Rom. 1. 16. 17. &amp; 4. 5.</note> Iuſtification thereunto. Now this is a myſterie to fleſh and blood (which would faine reioyce in it ſelfe) that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes ſhould be Iniquitie. Euen ſo is the Goſpell a myſterie, for by it the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of God is reueiled, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe could not be perceiued of fleſh and blood. For is it not a myſticall paradox to carnall reaſon, to ſay; God iuſtifieth the vngodly? which yet is cleere to him, who, vnderſtanding the Scriptures, doth not only abhorre his foule iniquitie, but alſo<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 9. Eſa. 64. 6.</note> diſclaimeth his owne defiled righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and by faith layeth hold on the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of God, which is only by Chriſt, or Who truſteth not to his righteouſnes inherent, which taſteth of the caske, but to righteouſnes imputed, which maketh vs bleſſed. Theſe things well conſidered; It may appeare, that as Chriſt is the myſtery of godlines, not only becauſe he is very God, though in the ſhape of a ſeruant, but alſo becauſe the Word of Chriſt, viz.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21060:19"/> the Goſpell, teacheth a myſtical righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes; So the Pope is Antichriſt, not only becauſe he is an aduerſarie in exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf aboue all that is called God, though he pretend to be the ſeruant of ſeruants, but alſo becauſe his doctrine is a myſticall iniquitie. Heere it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that on the forehead of the<note place="margin">Reuel. 17. 5. 9. 18.</note> Whore of Babylon (to wit Rome) was written this word, <hi>A mysterie;</hi> and it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to bee vnderſtood, that on the Popes Mitre is the ſame word ſet with precious ſtones. If then for the doctrine of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and merit by workes, the Church of Rome bee Antichriſtian, it followeth, that it is not Catholique, and therefore hath not continued an apparant member of the Catholique Church, euer ſince the Apoſtles time.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The later point inferred, may be the rather admitted, if wee marke well that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That the Myſtery of iniquitie<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 7</note> was working in his time. So that it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thoſe troublers (of whom me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion is made in the 4. ſection) ouergrew (as weeds) the good corne in time, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ſtill, vntill that myſterie of iniquity
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21060:20"/> was reuealed, and conſumed by the Spirit of God in the mouth of <hi>Luther,</hi> and other the ſeruants of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p n="7">7 For the better manifeſtation of this point, let vs ſeriouſly conſider, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Church of Rome were now an apparant member of the Catholique Church (which indeed is not to bee ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) yet ſith it is not the Catholique and inuiſible Church, but a viſible and particular Church, and hath not any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall promiſe, that it ſhould continue the ſame from the firſt conſtitution, how can we be aſſured, but that, in ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeeres, there haue been ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations and innouations, as well as in the Church of God among the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 4.</note> to whom pertained the adoption, glory, couenants, giuing of the Law, ſeruice of God, and the promiſes? And yet it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<note place="margin">2. Chro. 15. 3</note> of the Church: Now for a long ſeaſon, Iſrael hath been without the true God, and without Prieſt to teach, and without Law.</p>
            <p n="8">8 As for that promiſe of Chriſt, Thou<note place="margin">Mat. 16. 18.</note> art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this rocke I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhal not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21060:20"/> ouercome it, it appertaineth to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, as builded vpon Chriſt the<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 11.</note> only foundation of his Church, and not to the Church of Rome, more than to the Churches of Aſia, which are ouercome, or any other particular Church which may be ouercome; &amp; yet that promiſe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin">Gen. 9. 13.</note> inuiolable, as the couenant, whereof the Raine-bow is a ſigne, is inuiolable, notwithſtanding ſundrie particular coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries be ouerflowen.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Indeed <hi>Augustine</hi> did once take that Rocke to bee <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, and his ſucceſſors the Biſhops of Rome; but hee after altered that his opinion, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Rocke to ſignifie Chriſt, by <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed: For that Chriſt did not ſay to <hi>Peter,</hi> I will build me vpon thee, But his words were (ſo <hi>Augustine</hi> conceiued them) as if hee had ſaid, I will build thee vpon me, and not me vpon thee His mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">Col. 1. 24.</note> is: It is abſurd, that the Church which is Chriſts bodie (and is therefore called<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 12.</note> Chriſt; becauſe it cannot conſiſt without the head therof which is Chriſt himſelfe) ſhould be builded vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> who is but a member of the body. It is therfore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21060:21"/> that <hi>Peter</hi> being but a member, ſhould be builded vpon the body, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered together with the head.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Surely <hi>Augustine</hi> had reaſon to fly<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 6.</note> to the true Rocke of ſaluation. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the ſucceſſion of the Biſhops of Rome till his time, was an excellent teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth, becauſe they ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely maintained the faith touching the fundamentall points therof; yet he might well conſider that Perſonall ſucceſſion, without ſucceſſion in faith, is not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent confirmation, or authenticall note of a true Church. For at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople there hath bin an interrupted ſucceſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops til this day. And yet the Papiſts wil deny that to bee any part of Chriſt his Church, becauſe it reteineth not the true faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="11">11 But becauſe there is ſuch adoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſucceeding of <hi>Peter,</hi> and it is made a matter of ſo great importance, it is neceſſary to bee proued, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome bee <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors: Which how poſſibly Papiſts can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, I cannot ſee; ſith there is ſuch a diſagreement about his ſuppoſed imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21060:21"/> ſucceſſor; the Decrees affirming <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and writers of good regard, (as <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> and other) placing <hi>Linus</hi> next after <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 That this doubt whether the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome be <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, may be put out of all doubt, the Papiſts muſt neceſſarily proue foure things. 1. That <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was at Rome. 2. That he ſate Biſhop there 25. yeeres. 3. That he was vniuerſal Biſhop. And 4. That his vniuerſal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie was ſufficiently conueyed ouer to all that ſhould lawfully ſucceed him in that See. In any of which if they faile, the Popes authority falleth to the ground. For if <hi>Peter</hi> were neuer at Rome, how could he be Biſhop there? If not Biſhop at all, how vniuerſall Biſhop? If he had no ſuch authority himſelfe, how could it be conueyed ouer to his pretended ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors? And if there were not ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyance, how fruſtrate is the Popes claime? But that there be ſuch doubts in euery of theſe points, as the Papiſts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not cleerely reſolue, conſider well the foure next articles.</p>
            <p n="13">13 None doth ſimply deny, but that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21060:22"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> might haue been at Rome, as a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger; or for ſome ſhort abode, although ſo much be not manifeſt: But that he ſate Biſhop there, and that ſo many yeeres, is altogether vnlikely. For it not very likely, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaluting ſo many by name, as he doth in his Epiſtle to the Romans, but that hee would make ſome honorable mention of <hi>Peter?</hi> And wheras ſixe of his Epiſtles were dated at Rome, Is it not lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but that in ſome of them hee would ſpeake of <hi>Peter,</hi> if he had been there ſo long, and in ſuch authority, as he doth of <hi>Timothy,</hi> whoſe authoritie was leſſe, that thereby his exhortations, and reprouings might better preuaile? To ſay nothing that the Scriptures doe not in any place, ſignify that <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome: Which (in likelihood) ſhould haue bin done, if God had ſeene ſucceſſion of Biſhops at Rome from <hi>Peter,</hi> to be a matter of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as now it is made.</p>
            <p n="14">14 But ſay that he was at Rome, it will helpe the Papiſts nothing, except they can proue, that hee was alſo Biſhop of Rome. Whereof there is ſmall likelihood, if wee take this word Biſhop, not in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21060:22"/> large ſenſe, which comprehendeth Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and all Miniſters hauing authoritie; but in the ſtrict ſenſe, which ſignifieth a Miniſter intituled to a certaine place. For is it likely that <hi>Peter</hi> deſcended from the higheſt degree in the Church (of which al Apoſtles were) next to Chriſt the head, to the inferiour degree of a Biſhop? or Is<note place="margin">Matth. 18. 18. &amp; 28. 18. 19. 20.</note> it likely that hee who had authoritie throughout the whole world, as hee was an Apoſtle, was tied to a particular charge, as he was Biſhop?</p>
            <p n="15">15 But they ſay, He was Vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and therefore his authority was not reſtreined. They muſt needs ſay ſo, for elſe his ſuppoſed being Biſhop at Rome will ſtand them in no ſtead. But was his authoritie inlarged hereby? If no, (for how could hee haue a larger iuriſdiction, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Apoſtolical authority throughout the world?) what reaſon then can they giue, why he ſhould enioy that Vniuerſall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, rather by the name of a Biſhop, and that of a particular place, than by the name of an Apoſtle? Againe, Is it not ſtrange, that they cannot by any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proue this point, ſith it is of ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21060:23"/> conſequence with them, as that it bindeth their conſciences to the See of Rome? Nay rather the Scriptures ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. For it is recorded in holy Writ, That the Apoſtleſhip of the circumciſion<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 7. 8.</note> (that is, of the Iewes) was committed to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtleſhip of the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion (that is, of the Gentiles, ſuch were the Romans) was committed to <hi>Paul.</hi> Againe, Is it likely, that <hi>Paul</hi> who<note place="margin">Rom. 15. 20.</note> inforced himſelfe to preach the Goſpell, not where Chriſt was named, leſt hee ſhould haue built on another mans foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, would ſo intrude himſelfe into <hi>Peters</hi> office, as to meddle with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of ſo many Churches as he doth, (and that with all authoritie) in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Romans, and other his Epiſtles from Rome, and al this, without any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Peter,</hi> if <hi>Peter</hi> had been at Rome, and had ſuch an Vniuerſal authoritie? Sith <hi>Paul</hi> (as is ſaid) ioyned with himſelfe (for the more authorie of ſome of his Epiſtles) <hi>Timothy</hi> one of leſſe authority than <hi>Peter,</hi> and writeth to the Philippians, That he<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 20.</note> had none like minded to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that would faithfully care for their matters.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21060:23"/> Laſtly, It is vtterly vnlikely, That <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 11. &amp;c.</note> would haue reproued <hi>Peter</hi> to his face, and that openly, for withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the Gentiles, if <hi>Peter</hi> had had ſuch authoritie, as the Papiſts dreame of.</p>
            <p n="16">16 But ſuppoſe that <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome, and had ſuch authoritie, what is the Pope better for it, if it were not made ouer to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, by ſufficient conueyance? But in this poynt, which chiefely concernes the Pope, the Papiſts ſeeme vtterly to faile. For <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, reprooued <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople for indeuouring to obtaine the title of Vniuerſall Biſhop, and to haue his Church called the head of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, telling him that none of the Biſhops of Rome durſt take ſuch a title, though the Emperours began in Rome, were wont to abide there only, and did then intitle themſelues Emperours of Rome. Nay he told him yet more plainely, That whoſoeuer aſpired to bee Vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, was a fore-runner of Antichriſt. Whereby it is euident that in <hi>Gregories</hi> time, there was no knowledge of any conueyance of <hi>Peters</hi> ſuppoſed authority
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21060:24"/> made ouer to the Biſhops of Rome. But for al this peremptory iudgement of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> (ſurnamed The Great) within few yeeres after (about anno 607.) <hi>Boniface</hi> 3. obtained that title, with much ſuite and bribery, of <hi>Phocas</hi> an adulterer, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of his maſter (that Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Mauritius</hi>) with his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But ſucceeding Popes for the credit of that dignitie (being belike aſhamed of ſuch an inſtitution) pretended to hold the ſame by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Donation</hi> of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour. So that al this while, there was no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyance of that authority from <hi>Peter</hi> that yet came to light. At laſt, the Pope (being come to the height of his pride) thought it a ſcorne to be beholden to <hi>Constantine,</hi> or any of them all, and therefore laid hold vpon thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Thou art Peter, &amp;c.</hi> But what hold he hath by them is partly ſhewed before, and is further to be conſidered, In that the Popes champion (father <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> made a Cardinall for his deſerts) doth confeſſe, that this Vniuerſal Biſhopricke is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Pope by a conueyance indeed, but not of the word, but of tradition.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21060:24"/> Thus you may diſcouer the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of an article of the Popiſh creed, viz. That the Pope hath Apoſtolicall authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole Church, as he is <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Leauing theſe doubts touching the pretended ſucceſſors of <hi>Peter,</hi> and commending them to the aduiſed exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Reader, I proceed brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proue (in more ſpeciall manner) the Church of Rome not to haue been an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant member of the Catholike Church, euer ſince the Apoſtles time. I ſay Briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For if I ſhould demonſtrate (as I could) the many, &amp; groſſe errors of the Church, both in doctrine and diſcipline (vnder which word I vnderſtand the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, and the Liturgie) and if withall, I ſhould paint out the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die tyrannie thereof, in perſecuting the children of God, it would appeare more than manifeſt that it is, and hath bin long an apparant member, not of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, but of the malignant Church: But then I ſhould be longer than I may, by reaſon of neceſſary buſines, or need, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering ſo many bookes are written of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21060:25"/> thoſe Arguments. I will therefore only propound ſome few things of many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Pope, whom the Papiſts make the head of the Catholike Church. So that as a member of a mans body, is but dead if it receiue no life from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall head, ſo a particular Church is (in their opinion) no apparant member of the Catholique Church, which is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the iuriſdiction of the Biſhop of Rome: From hence it followeth, That if the head be dead, the body muſt needs be dead: and, if the Pope be not, the Church of Rome cannot be an apparant member of the Catholique Church: But the Pope is not. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 The Pope is Antichriſt, and hath been ſo long, therefore the Church of Rome is not, and for a long time hath not been an apparant member of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church: For as his See is the ſeat of<note place="margin">Reuel. 17. 9. 18.</note> the whore of Babylon, to wit the Citie builded vpon 7. hilles, namely Rome, ſo he hath the properties of Antichriſt: For he ſitteth in the Temple as God, In char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 4</note> the conſcience as ſtrictly with his decrees, and traditions, as with the Word
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21060:25"/> of God, from whence the other haue no warrant, and In auouching himſelfe to be free from error, which is proper to God. 2. He exalteth himſelfe aboue all that is<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4. 2. Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> called God, In eſteeming himſelfe as far aboue the Emperour (who muſt hold his ſtirrup, &amp; on whoſe necke he muſt tread) as the Sunne is aboue the Moone, and<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1.</note> therefore hee will not bee ſubiect to any Magiſtrate, contrary to the expreſſe word of God. 3. He is an aduerſary to Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> howſoeuer he pretend to be his Vicar; but<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 22.</note> therefore Antichriſt in deed, ſeeing this word Antichriſt ſignifieth For Chriſt, and yet Againſt Chriſt. I ſay an aduerſary, not only In teaching Iuſtification by workes, to the preiudice of Chriſts death, for if<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 21.</note> Righteouſnes be by the Law, Chriſt died in vaine, but alſo, In teaching that by Chriſt we are freed from the guiltines of ſinne, but not from the puniſhment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and yet the Popes pardons, and the breaden God of his owne creation, can do as much good to ſoules frying in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, as to all, that pay well for them<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 1. 3.</note> while they liue on the earth. 4. He teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth doctrines of diuels, forbidding to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21060:26"/> marry, and comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to abſtaine from meates, which God hath created to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with thankeſ-giuing, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which beleeue and know the truth. And 5. Hee<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. 3.</note> denieth Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, In affirming Chriſt his body to be, by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation, in ſo many places, as where Maſſe is ſaid. As the Anabaptiſts likewiſe deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, In af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Chriſt to haue brought his fleſh from heauen.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Againe; Sith the Pope (as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed head) is of the eſſence and forme of the Church of Rome, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the Church of Rome hath not been alwaies an apparant member of the Catholike Church (according to the ſenſe of the Papiſts themſelues) if it can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that often, &amp; ſomtimes many yeeres together, there hath been no apparant Pope: But that is not impoſſible to bee proued: For firſt it is to be noted with a <hi>memorandum,</hi> That by the ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, Pope <hi>Ioan</hi> was deliuered of a child as ſhe was going ſolemnly on proceſſion in the middeſt of the open ſtreet, and in the preſence of the people.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21060:26"/> As if God had ſaid from heauen, Behold the Whore of Babylon. Secondly, It is worthy the obſeruation, That <hi>Stephen</hi> 6. and <hi>Sergius</hi> the third proceeded againſt <hi>Formoſus,</hi> as againſt an vnlawfull Pope, both taking him out of the graue, ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſgraded him. The former ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Councel, attired him with the pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall robes, plucked them off againe, put on Lay-mans apparell, cut off the two fingers of his right hand, caſt them into Tiber, buried him in Lay-mens buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and diſanulled his decrees. The other ſet him in the Popes chaire; drew him thence againe, cut off his head, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three fingers; hurled body and al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the riuer, &amp; recondemned all his actes, ſo that it was needful to admit them new to orders, whom hee had made Prieſts. Thirdly, It is not to be neglected as not worth the reading, That ſixe Popes (viz. <hi>Clement 5. Iohn 23. Benedict 12. Clement 6. Innocent</hi> 6. and <hi>Vrban</hi> 5.) their See was 70. yeers together at Auignion in <hi>France.</hi> Where Popes were elected, liued, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that ſome of them neuer ſaw Rome. This I ſay is not to bee neglected. For if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21060:27"/> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarch of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the title of Vniuerſal Biſhop, becauſe the Emperours had then their ſeat there, howſoeuer they then bare the title of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of Rome. If <hi>Peter</hi> were therefore the Biſhop of Rome, becauſe he had his ſeat there, and there died, as Papiſts doe ſuppoſe, and If by the holy daies for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> chaire at Antioch, and Rome, Papiſts ſhew their iudgement to be, That it is of the eſſence of a Biſhop to ſit in the See, whereof hee hath the title, for otherwiſe they need not make ſuch adoe, to proue that <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome, ſeeing it were ſufficient to proue (if they could) that he accepted the title, then thoſe 6. Popes, howſoeuer they were in title Biſhops of Rome, yet in truth they were Biſhops of Auignion and therefore no apparant ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of <hi>Peter,</hi> and therefore no appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant heads of the Church, and therefore for 70. yeeres the Church of Rome was not an apparant member of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, according to the ſenſe of the Papiſts themſelues. Fourthly, <hi>Onuphrius</hi> (a Popiſh writer) telleth of 30. Schiſmes in the Church of Rome. Of which the 29.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21060:27"/> laſted 50. yeeres together. Wherin there were ſometimes two Popes together, and ſometimes three. All which three were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued by the Councel of <hi>Constance.</hi> Can any ſay, that all this while there was an apparant head? If not, it muſt neceſſarily follow, That the Church of Rome hath not been euer ſince the Apoſtles time an apparant member of the Catholique Church, according to the ſenſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelues.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Laſtly, As when the eye is darke,<note place="margin">Matth. 6. 23</note> the whole body muſt needs be darke: So, if the head, viz. the Pope, be ſo corrupt, as that it cannot be perceiued to be an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t member of the Catholike Church, how can the Church of Rome, whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is altogether in that head, be an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant member? But moſt of the Popes haue been ſuch: <hi>Ergo.</hi> For howſoeuer that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be verified of al the Popes, which was ſaid of <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. commonly called A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell incarnat, That he entered like a <hi>Fox,</hi> raigned like a <hi>Lion,</hi> and died like a <hi>Dog,</hi> yet ſome of them entered by Coniurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or the diuels helpe, as <hi>Siluester</hi> 2. and <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. firſt called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> or The
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21060:28"/> brand of Hell. Some by harlots, as <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> 1. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 11. Some by poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their predeceſſors, as <hi>Damaſus,</hi> who alſo did drinke of the ſame cup; and the ſaid <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> who (beſides his Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) made way to the Popedome by poyſoning ſixe of his predeceſſors; and many by Simony or Violence. Were they apparant members of the Catholique Church, when they were Popes? Nay ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry of them were heretiques. As <hi>Liberius</hi> was an Arrian: <hi>Honorius</hi> 1. a Monothelite: <hi>Anastaſius</hi> a Neſtorian: <hi>Iohn</hi> 2 2. denied the Life to come, and the reſurrection of the body, and this was laid to his charge when he was depoſed by the Councell of <hi>Constance:</hi> and <hi>Eugenius</hi> 4. was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and depoſed as an heretique in the Councell of <hi>Baſil.</hi> As for their Liues, In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all, it is no leſſe truly, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid of <hi>Gregory</hi> 1. That he was the worſt Biſhop, but beſt Pope of Rome. But ſome of them <hi>Platina</hi> (no Proteſtant) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Beaſts, and Monſters, and of <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. Cardinall <hi>Turrecremata</hi> writeth thus: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the life of this Pope was deteſtable, therefore Chriſt himſelf gaue out the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21060:28"/> of condemnation. For while he was abuſing a certaine mans wife, the diuell ſtroke him ſodainly, and ſo he died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance. To ſet downe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the monſtrous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of moſt Popes, is too large and too filthy a field for me to walke in; I will therefore ſhut vp with the words of <hi>Genebrard</hi> (a Popiſh Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler) who writeth thus: For the ſpace al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of ſeuen-ſcore yeeres, and ten, from <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. to <hi>Leo</hi> 9. about fiftie Popes did reuolt wholy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vertue of their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, and were Apoſtaticall rather than Apoſtolicall. Yea ſome did get into the See, by force or bribery; Wherefore it is no maruell, if they were monſtrous, ſith they entered in, not by the dore, but by a poſterne gate.</p>
            <p>To conclude, If the Church of Rome be not the Catholique Church, becauſe it is confined, viſible, &amp; faileth in the faith, without which faith, perſonall ſucceſſion is of no validitie; If it haue no promiſe of perpetuity, the words of Chriſt to <hi>Peter</hi> not ſeruing the turne; and therefore may be ouercome as well as the Church of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, whereunto the promiſes did apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21060:29"/> If Papiſts cannot proue, that <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome, nor that hee was Biſhop there, nor that he was Vniuerſall Biſhop, nor that his authority was ſufficiently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed ouer to the Biſhops of Rome, vpon which ſucceſſion ſtandeth the being of that Church. If the Pope (vpon whom as their head the Church of Rome depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) be Antichriſt, and ſundry times, yea many yeeres together, there hath bin no apparant Pope at all, and moſt Popes haue been no apparant members of the Catholike Church, becauſe of their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies or monſtrous liues, it followeth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that the Church of Rome is not the Catholique Church, neither hath bin an apparant member of the ſame, euer ſince the Apoſtles time. And therefore it is to be wondered that any Chriſtian man or woman, ſhould bee ſo ſimple, as to hang their ſaluation vpon ſuch a Synagogue, as out of which, God from heauen biddeth his people to depart: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</hi> 18. 4.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="position">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21060:29"/>
            <head>THE THIRD POSITION. PRIESTS ARE EXECV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not for Religion, but for <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not to bee denied, that Prieſts are executed for <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Popes Primacie,</hi> and reconciling to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Church of Rome, &amp;c. which are points of their ſuppoſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: But yet they are not executed for theſe (or like) points or parts as they be religious, but as they bee trayterous, or dangerous to the State, in ciuill conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For, if Prieſts were executed for theſe, or like poynts, as they be religious, then the Church would proceed againſt them in Eccleſiaſticall maner, before the ſecular power execute ciuill puniſhment. As againſt Anabaptiſtes, and other in this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21060:30"/> Queenes raigne, hath bene performed. So that Prieſts their caſe differeth from Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets only <hi>Secundum magis &amp; minus,</hi> the one being more dangerous in ciuil conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration then the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, they ſhould be executed as wel for affirming the Popes primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. (as Story for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanure, though) beyond ſeas. For ſuch affirming the primacie and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c. are as damnable in religious conſideration on one ſide of the ſeas, as on the other, but not ſo dangerous to our ſtate in ciuill conſideration.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, they ſhould be executed as well for other points of popery: as giuing the glory of the Creator (to wit prayer and praiſe) to creatures, Angels, Saints, ſtockes, and ſtones, &amp;c. being no leſſe damnable then ſuch affirming the Popes primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. in religious conſideration, but not ſo dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill conſideration. As may appeare by a like caſe propounded.</p>
            <p>If Anabaptiſtes, denying <hi>magiſtracy,</hi> and <hi>that Chriſt tooke fleſh of the Virgin Mary,</hi> ſhould ſwarme in England, and if
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21060:30"/> Magiſtrates ſhould puniſh in a more ciuil manner of proceeding, not the latter (though no leſſe damnable, as it is religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) but the former, being more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the ſtate in ciuill conſideration, who would ſay, that Anabaptiſtes did ſuffer for religion, and not for treaſon or felony?</p>
            <p n="4">4 That affirming the Popes primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. may appeare direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill conſideration, and therefore trayterous; it is to be knowne &amp; conſidered, that Pope Pius Quintus (by his bull declaratory) pronounced our gracious and Chriſtian Queene <hi>an hereticke,</hi> and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all ſuch as yeeld obedience to her. If then the Popes authority be perſwaded as a matter of conſcience, &amp; if by reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation her Maieſties ſubiects become vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed members of ſuch an head as is her capitall enemy, we may be aſſured that ſo many as are ſo perſwaded and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, are prepared to obey the Pope, and diſobey the Prince. Is not then ſuch affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Popes primacy and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c. dangerous to the ſtate, in ciuill
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21060:31"/> conſideration, and therefore trayterous?</p>
            <p n="5">5 In that I ſay (prepared) it is yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be knowne and conſidered: that whereas the Northerne Earles had ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in executing the ſaid Bull, other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes were fruſtrated, and the hope of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts their preſent preuailing much failed Parſons and Campian (Engliſh Prieſts) being to come into England to vrge the ſayd Bull, and doubting that (in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour thereof) it would not be readily obeyed, did craue and obtaine of Pope Gregory the thirteenth, this expoſition more plauſible to Papiſts, but more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſtate: <hi>That the ſaid Bull may alway bind the Queene and heretiques: but Catholikes</hi> (that is Papiſts) <hi>in no ſort, things ſtanding as they do, but then only, when there may be publike execution thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Philopater a louer of his country (as he pretendeth by that fained name) no Engliſhman (if ye will beleeue him) yet deſcended of the Engliſh nation (as he ſaith himſelfe) in a poyſonfull and trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous booke, often printed in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beyond the ſeas (ſuch liking find ſuch books with ſuch ſubiects as Papiſts be)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21060:31"/> graunteth that Prieſts are ſent, with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> from the Pope, to pardon, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, reconcile, and teach (according to the Bull expounded) that ſubiects are not to obey the Queene in ſpiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but in ciuill, and <hi>that for the preſent ſtate of things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 What is implied in this laſt clauſe, Philopater himſelfe diſcouereth when he ſaith, that it is agreed among diuers Lawyers and ſchoolemen, that if a Prince<note place="margin">Sect. 3.</note> faile from the Romane faith, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to withdraw other, ſubiects <hi>may and ought</hi> oppoſe themſelues, &amp; depoſe their Princes, <hi>if they haue force.</hi> Which prouiſo, he inculcateth and vrgeth with this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: <hi>Laſt religion ſhould be indamaged, and aduanced, attempts not preuailing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 The ſame Philopater doth peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily pronounce as tyrannicall, this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion moued to Prieſts, fugitiues, recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, and ſuch like: <hi>If the Pope, or other in his behalfe and cauſe of religion, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the land, what part would you take, the Popes or the Princes?</hi> His reaſon of miſlike is, <hi>becauſe a right Papiſt cannot anſwere freely thereunto, without offence to God or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21060:32"/> Caeſar.</hi> As if God were offended, if Caeſar defended againſt the Pope.</p>
            <p>By which expoſition of the bull, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Prieſts, and miſlike of a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ſo neceſſary it doth clearely appeare that the end of affirming the Popes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and reconciling, &amp;c. is to prepare her Maieſties ſubiects to be ready (vpon paine of excommunication) to ioyne with ſuch forces as ſhall be imploied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Queene and ſtate, in a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded cauſe of religion. Is not this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the ſtate in ciuill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, and therefore trayterous?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Let the affects and effects of ſuch teachers and ſchollers be obſerued, and the truth of this aſſertion will be ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as that nothing can be more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. To let paſſe their broad ſpeeches, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and where they dare: their concealing and abetting traytors, and trayterous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, as they may (poſſibly) without danger, their reioycing at, and ſpreading abroad newes, importing ſucceſſe to the Pope, though danger to the Prince, &amp;c. To omit (I ſay) theſe and many ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of their trayterous affection, the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21060:32"/> ſhamefull practiſes of many, bewray the Popiſh preparation of moſt, if opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie once ſerue. Many haue been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt her Maieſties perſon, to take away her life. <hi>But O Lord haue mercy vpon vs, to preſerue her.</hi> Many haue bin the treaſons againſt the Land to deſtroy it. <hi>But O holy one of Iſrael defend this thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</hi> Who haue bin the authors and actors of all theſe tragicall attempts, but ſuch teachers and ſchollers? What were the Rebels in the North? And were they not prouoked to rebellion by <hi>Nicholas Morton</hi> Prieſt, ſent from Pope <hi>Pius,</hi> to vrge the execution of his bull? What were the Rebels in Ireland? And was not <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Sanders</hi> a <hi>Iudas</hi> (that is) a leader to the Popes army, that came in pretence to relieue them? <hi>Parry</hi> and <hi>Sommeruile</hi> went about to murther her Maieſtie. The one was encouraged in his diuelliſh enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, by Cardinall <hi>Como,</hi> in the name of the Pope: and ſhall we thinke that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wanted the holy counſell of <hi>Hall</hi> the Prieſt arraigned? <hi>Babington</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, conſpired againſt Prince &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Was not <hi>Ballard</hi> Prieſt a chiefe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21060:33"/> to them? and did not <hi>Bost</hi> a Prieſt keepe counſell (at leaſt) as he lately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed? If then Teachers and Schollers, Prieſts and Papiſts, concurre in ſeeking and following all opportunities to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert our State, can any other end be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined of Prieſts, their perſwading, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling, but to prepare their Schollers to ioyne together againſt Prince and country, when force ſhall anſwere their affection?</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the multitude of reſolued Papiſts, be thus poyſoned and prepared, let this be your laſt conſideration for this time, and not the leaſt at any time. That as the King of Aſhur purpoſing to beſiege Hieruſalem, ſent from <hi>Laciſh Rabſhaketh</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 32. 9. 12. 13.</note> and others, to weaken the hands of the people, by diſgracing their King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah,</hi> as one without religion, in that he had taken away Altars, and defaced high places; and by aduancing <hi>Saneherib,</hi> as one that preuailed againſt all Gods: So theſe Locuſts, which haue faces of men,<note place="margin">Reuel. 9. 3. 78. 10. 11.</note> and haire of women, but the ſtings of ſcorpions in their tailes, to wit, Prieſts, who pretend a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der care of ſauing ſoules
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21060:33"/> in the beginning, but intend a cruell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Life and Land in the end, are ſent into this Realme by their King (the<note place="margin">Iſa. 7. 4.</note> Angell of the bottomleſſe pit, out of the ſmoke thereof, namely, by the Pope in his fume, but without flame I truſt) before inuaſion intended, to weaken the hands, and withdraw the hearts of the people, from our gracious Queene, by diſgracing her Maieſtie, as one without religion, in that ſhee hath taken away ſacrificing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and defaced religious houſes; and by aduancing their King, as one that preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth againſt all Gods, all States, all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions. The like practiſe of ſending Prieſts to prepare people againſt the comming in of Spaniards, is to bee perceiued in Scotland.</p>
            <p n="11">11 What ſucceſſe this deuice hath, is alſo to be conſidered. The Pope is certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi> and the King of Spaine by <hi>Parſons</hi> the Prieſt, that there ſhall be found (ready ſecretly within her Maieſties dominions) many thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people, that wil be ready to aſſiſt ſuch power as ſhall be ſet on land. Of whoſe names they haue deliuered bead-roles,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21060:34"/> eſpecially of ſuch as dwel in port Townes and on the ſea-coaſt, with aſſurance that Prieſts ſhall continue their reconciled people, in their lewde conſtancy. So hath her Maieſtie publiſhed in her Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Anno</hi> 1591. But <hi>Philopater</hi> denieth it,<note place="margin">Sect. 4.</note> impudently and barely without any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But if <hi>Ballard</hi> Prieſt ſent ſuch a bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role into Spaine, and <hi>Throgmorton</hi> had gathered the names of popiſh Noblemen and Gentlemen, to the ſame purpoſe: It may bee (in reaſon) ſuppoſed, that to Prieſts intelligence is ſent by Prieſts, what ſchollers they haue perſwaded and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Treaſon and Rebellion.</p>
            <p>To conclude, 1. If the Church proceed not againſt Prieſts in Eccleſiaſticall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, before the Secular power execute them. 2. If Prieſts ſuffer not for affirming the Popes Primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. beyond ſeas. 3. If Prieſts be not executed for other points of Popery, no leſſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable then theſe, as they bee religious. 4. But if the Pope by his Bull, hath vpon paine of Excommunication diſcharged her Maieſties ſubiects of their allegeance. 5. If Papiſts be diſpenſed with, for obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21060:34"/> her Maieſtie till time ſerue to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. 6. If Prieſts come of purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile and teach according to the Bull expounded. 7. If it bee a Catholique do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that ſubiects hauing force, ought to depoſe their Prince, maintaining Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion contrary to the Church of Rome: and 8. In that caſe to ioyne with forreigne power. 9. If maiſters and ſchollers haue from time to time attempted to put the ſaid Bull in execution. 10. If Prieſts bee ſent before inuaſion to prepare the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and 11. If thouſands be notified euen by Prieſts prepared: then it may be auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that Prieſts are not executed for affirming the Popes Primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. as they be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, but as they be trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, or dangerous to the State in ciuill conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
